We start on the middle of ח' עמוד ב', Chet Amud Bet,
which is in this middle of this fascinating story about the sages
of Athens.
And we pick up, so we had the first question which had
to do with they asked him about why would they give somebody
a woman higher than his station, tried to give an explanation for
what that meant. Now we go on, which it says
like this.
גברא דאוזיף וטריף. Gavra de'ozif vetarif. The line starts with the word
וטריף. vetarif. It is about 20 lines from the bottom. Okay, so
if somebody lent money and then had to go seize the property
in payment of his debt, the person was not, you know, was
not, he did not get his money back easily. מאי חזי דהדר
אוזיף, Mai chazi dehadar ozif, what would motivate him to lend again,
seeing as how he had risked his principal and it was so
difficult to get his money
back? אמר להו, Amar lehu, so he said back to them, גברא
אזל לאגמא, Gavra azal le'agma, let's give, I'll give you an example,
let's say somebody went into the forest, literally swamp, but here in
this context forest. קטף קמא טונא, Kataf kama tuna, first he cut
down the first like load of wood. ולא מצי טעין ליה, Velo
matzi teivei, it was too big for him, he couldn't carry it.
So what's he going to do there, like what, leave the wood?
So קטף ומנח עלייהו, Katu u'manach alaihu, so he keeps on chopping
wood and adding to the pile of what he's already chopped. עד
דרמי איניש, Ad de'rami inish, until somebody else comes along ומטלי ליה,
u'matli lei, and is able to give him a hand. So what
exactly does that mean? It sounds like he's saying, look, you know,
if at first you don't succeed, try, try again. Okay, so, you
know, you know, yes, you did it, it wasn't successful the first
time, but you don't stop doing it, eventually maybe, you know, in
this scenario eventually somebody else comes along and helps you, presumably the
is, you know, the next guy you lend will be better, will
be more trustworthy, and keep at it and maybe ultimately you'll find
the right people to lend to and it'll make a success of
the venture. But it's a little strange, like exactly what was the
question, what was the answer, and you know, the מהר"ל Maharal points
out where that the next questions are going to be like complete
riddles, like not make any sense. Here at least it's a reasonable
question, it's a reasonable answer, you don't understand what the big meaning
of it all is, but at least it's reasonable. So,
so, you know, here both the מהר"ל Maharal and the מהרש"א Marsha
in explaining this have a pretty similar explanation and they say that
the point sort of is, it's like, you know, reading this as
sort of the subtext about Greek versus, you know, Jewish wisdom or
just the whole whether whatever, you know, or the basis basically or
just the success of Rome versus the lack of success of the
Jews in this world. Anyway, so that the question was, hey look
you guys, you know, you
did מצוות mitzvot and and you didn't fulfill them. It's like you
lent, you know, you're like the borrowing side, you borrowed the money
and you didn't pay it up and God had to collect His
debt. How did God have to collect His debt? You know, you
got driven from the land, the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash was destroyed.
So what makes you think
that God wants to keep up that relationship? If somebody lent money
and the person didn't pay him back or whatever, he's not going
to want to, you know, lend him again. So the answer is,
look, we keep on doing our מצוות, mitzvot, we keep on chopping
wood, we keep on doing our מצוות mitzvot and eventually, you know,
you know, other people come and other people are helping us or
whatever and it's even if one generation, you know, didn't succeed, but
but ultimately we believe that we keep on doing
מצוות mitzvot and further generations and other people that come along the
way and that helps and and ultimately, you know, it sustains the
relationship and we will be redeemed even if right now we are
not, we are not redeemed. So read that way, no, I was
giving the more or less the way the מהר"ל Maharal and the
מהרש"א Marsha read it. So it's sort of similar to the point
before about the Greeks sort of saying, look, you know, you're, you
know, you have it bad in this world, what makes you think
that God still desires you? So trying to read it in a
somewhat analogous way this way, although it's a little bit more forced
here, yes.
That's an example where you absolutely can't read something literally because if
you take this literally, you have the banking crisis.
Well, yes, you should not keep on, you know, you know, throwing
good money after bad and making bad bets. Right, so you keep
on, the point is you keep on, you try, you hope that
the next, you know, doesn't mean that you give up on it
altogether, you try to, you know, you try to have a little
wisdom in your next, you know, as you keep on going forward,
yes.
And is it the same Rabbi Yehoshua who's the תנא, Tanna, the
teacher of Rabbi Akiva?
No, this is Rabbi Yehoshua, I don't think that's Rabbi Yehoshua ben
Chananya, that's not the Rabbi Yehoshua of Rabbi Akiva. Okay, so anyway,
so let's keep on going. Those lead to somewhat understandable questions and
answers. Now we get to things which are fundamentally more just riddles.
So let's take a look.
Okay, so it says like this.
אמרו ליה אימא לן מילי דבדיאי, Amru lei eima lan mili debedai,
so
they said to him, tell us a riddle essentially. means like some
type of a, like he says some, some falsehood or something, something
made up, but essentially it means tell us a riddle. So אמר
להו, Amar lehu, so he said to them, הויא ההיא קודנייתא, Havé
hahu kudnisa, there was a,
there was a mule, a female mule, דילדה, deyaldah, that gave birth,
והוה תלי לה פתקא, vahavi telei pitka, and on it was and
around it, around it was like a, like a sign, וכתיב ביה,
vechtiv beh, and on the sign of this mule was written, דמסיק
ביה אבא מאה אלפא זוזי, demasai bebei aba me'a alfa zuzei, that
somebody lent my, you know, my father's house a hundred thousand zuz.
Okay.
So אמרו ליה, amru leh, they said to him, וקודנייתא מי ילדה,
vekudnisa miyalda, do mules give birth? אמר
להו, Amar lehu, he said back to them, היינו מילי דבדיותא, haynu
milei debeduyei, that was the riddle that I told you. Okay, thank
you very much. All right, let's keep on going. מילחא כי סריא
במאי מלחי לה, milcha ki sarya bemai malchi lei,
so then they asked him, okay, if salt goes, starts to go
bad, what do you salt it with? Because you use salt as
a preservative, let's say the salt itself goes bad, what do you,
what do you salt it with? So he said, אמר להו, Amar
lehu, he said to them, בשילתא דקודנייתא, besilta dekudnisa, with the afterbirth
of a mule. So they said, once again with the mules giving
birth, so they said ומי איכא שילתא לקודנייתא, umi ika silta lekudnisa,
does a mule have an afterbirth? So he said ומילחא מי סריא,
umilcha mi sarya, and does salt go bad? Okay. But
so now moving on, they said בנו לן ביתא באוירא, banei lan
beita ba'avira, build us a house in the heaven, in the air,
באוירא דעלמא, ba'avira de'alma, in the sort of air of the world,
build us a house in the air. So some people are very
good at that about building castles in the air. Some people would
think that's a specialty of the rabbis. Anyway, אמר
שם, Amar shem, so he said a divine name, תלא בין רקיעא
לארעא, tala bein raki'a le'ara, who knows, he suspended himself between the
heaven and the earth. אמר להו, Amar lehu, and he said to
them, אסיקו לי לבני וטיני, asiku li livnei vetinei, okay, you asked
me to build a castle or build a house, here I am,
just now hand please, please hand me bricks and mortar so I
can build this castle up in the air. Presumably they couldn't get
them because he was up in the air. So, and that's the
end of that's the end of that story. All right. מציעתא דעלמא
היכא, metiatza de'alma haycha, then they said to him, where's the middle
of the world? זקפא לאצבעיה, zachfa le'etzbe'ei,
he stuck out his finger. אמר להו הכא, Amar lehu hacha, he
said to them, here. Okay. ומי יימר, umi yemar, and says, how
can you prove that's the middle of the world? So he says,
אייתו אשלי ומשחו, aiti ashlei umshchi, I'll prove it to you if
you can bring me ropes, we can measure. So if you can
bring me enough of a measuring rope to measure the length of
the world, then I'll prove to you that this is halfway in
the world. There obviously seems to be some big subtext going on
here. I could tell you what the מהרש"א Maharsha says but I
don't think it's it's so so satisfying. I mean he tries to
read this ongoing about you know,
like I'll just give you one sense of it like the sense
about the middle of the world and whatever. Again it's a sense
of like an orientation towards the physical, an orientation towards God. You
know, if it's an orientation towards the physical, so you it's you
know, if sort of God is everywhere then also everywhere is the
center because you know God's presence is everywhere, so therefore it's a
sense of infinite and if it's infinite then everything is the center.
Right, I'm the center of the world. Right, yeah. If I stick
up my finger it's the center of the world.
Oh, but he was the one that's saying my finger is the
center of the world.
No, but he pointed to just wherever he was.
Wherever it doesn't matter, it's always man is the intersection between the
divine and the physical.
Oh, that's interesting. Okay.
But and then you know if you have a much more physical
orientation, so how do you know the measure of the world? You'd
have to actually get out a get out a measure, you know,
what do you call it? tape and literally measure. So you know,
so you guys your physical orientation there's no you know there's no
way you can measure but I who, anyway I don't know.
Does the גמרא Gemara explain it?
Who? No, he doesn't really. He just does the rest of the
stuff, he only explains the first two. He says the rest of
the stuff was there was no sort of profound subtext. All right,
anyway, okay, so where
are we?
Okay, so that's also like building, building the building the house between
the heaven and the earth, you know, it's sort of again like,
you know, connecting between the divine and this world and the sense
of מצוות mitzvos and our relationship to God tries to read that
as some of the ongoing subtext. Okay, moving on,
where are we? אית
לן בירא בדברא, ith lan bira bedavra, we have a well out
in the, out
outside, out in the field. עיילה למתא, aila lamata, bring the well
to the city. Sounds almost like a Wise Men of Chelm story,
right? You remember that one of them like that about bringing... אמר
להו אחווי לי חבלי מפארי ועיילינא, amar lehu achviti li chavlei mipari
va'aila,
so okay, if you can string for me a rope out of
bran, out of flour, then I'll use that rope to draw the
well in. All right, so the same way you can't make a
rope that way you can't bring in a well. I don't know.
אית לן ריחייא דתבירא, ith lan recha d'atvira, we have a broken
millstone. חייטי, haytei,
sew it up. אמר, amar, so he said to them, כוחו לי
מיניה גרדי, kukhu li minei darda'ei, fine, if you can make some
strings out of the out of the millstone because how do you
sew up a garment? use threads from the garment itself to weave
it back together. So if you can make me threads from the
millstone, then וחייטי, v'khaytai, I'll sew it up for you. Okay, משרדא
דסכינא במאי קטלי? Mishrada d'sakhina b'mai katli?
How would you cut down a like a bed of knives? So
he said, בקרנא דחמרא, B'karna d'khamra, with the horn of a, with
the horn of a donkey. ומי איכא קרנא לחמרא? U'mi ika karna
l'khamra? Is there a horn of a donkey? ומי איכא משרדא דסכינא?
U'mi ika mishrada d'sakhina?
Is there such a thing as a bed of knives? All right,
אייתו ליה תרי ביעי, Aitu lei trei beiei, they brought him two
eggs. אמר להו הי דזיקא אוכמתא והי דזיקא חיורתא? Amar lehu hai
d'ziksa ukhmita v'hai d'ziksa khivarta? Which one came from the black hen,
which one came from the white hen? So אייתו להו, aitu lehu,
so he brought
to them תרי גביני, trei gavinei, two rounds of cheese. אמר להו
הי דעיזא אוכמתא והי דעיזא חיורתא? Amar lehu hai d'iza ukhmita v'hai
d'iza khivarta? Which one is from the black goat and which one's
from the white goat? So basically the same question. No fair, we
asked you first. Okay, but then he says, ורצוצא דמית מהיכא נפיק?
V'rtzutza d'mis me'heikha nafik?
Now this one is interesting. This one you can sort of get
a greater sense of the religious or maybe a subtext here. ורצוצא
דמית מהיכא נפיק? V'rtzutza d'mis me'heikha nafik? When a chick dies in
the egg, how does the soul escape? Where does the soul go
out? Because it's trapped. No, רצוצא rtzutza is the chick. מית mis
is die. Where does it go out?
Just where's the word for soul in there?
There isn't, it's implicit. Okay, so the point is it's trapped in
the egg. So he says, מהיכא דעל נפיק. Me'heikha d'al nafik. Exactly,
where there, where does the spirit go out? So he says, מהיכא
דעל נפיק, Me'heikha d'al nafik, the same way the spirit got into
the egg, it goes out of the egg. So here at least
it seems a little bit is that with a very sort of
physical worldly orientation, if you have an idea of spirit, it still
is an idea that is more sort of a physical idea like
wind, רוח. ruach. So therefore how can it get into the egg,
you know, how does it get out if it's trapped? And his
answer is, you know, it's non-physical, so the same way it can
be it can go into the chick when it's born and grow
in the egg, but does it's basically the answer is that our
sense of spirit is a totally non-physical sense. All right, אחוי לן
מנא דלא שוי חבליה. Akhvi lan mana d'lo shavei khavlei.
So he brought,
so they said to him, show us a vessel that is not
worth its damage. That sort of the effort for the vessel is
not worth the loss when trying to preserve it. So let's see
what he does. אייתי בודיא, Aiti budya, he brought a mat, like
a reed mat. פשטיה, Pashtei, he opened it up. לא הוי עייל
בבבא, Lo havi ayil b'vava, couldn't get in the door. So how
do you get a mat in the door? אמר להו אייתו מרא,
Amar lehu aitu mara, get me like a, like a whatever, a
hatchet. סתריה, Satrei, and he chopped down the door in order to
get the mat in the door. I had a couch like that
once. Okay, so היינו מנא דלא שוי חבליה. Hainu mana d'lo shavei
khavlei. Actually what I had to do is I had to call
these people, which is somebody is somebody called the sofa doctor. You
might have even read this in the New York Times, because even
the sofas that look like one piece and they're impossible, there's really
a way you can totally disassemble and reassemble a sofa. So I
had to whatever. Anyway, so I had a case like that anyway,
so they had to chop down the whole door. Anyway, היינו מנא
דלא שוי חבליה. Hainu mana d'lo shavei khavlei. This is a vessel
that is not worth the damage. Okay, somehow that's if you picked
up all the subtext then כל הכבוד kol hakavod to you. Somebody
told me there's a whole book written about trying to unpack this
גמרא. Gemara. Anyway, for now we will just accept the fact that
if the מהר"ל Maharal figured that there was no real point in
the rest of the question, he just said it was a battle
of wits, but there wasn't a subtext. And then he tried to
just explain what the battle of wits was. Anyway, let's move on.
אסינהו כל חד וחד. Asinhu kol khad v'khad. So he brought each
one into his boat because he won. He won. Okay, yeah, won't
you follow? You see that he won. Are you just a classic
Jewish joke that basically sounds like this? Do people know the joke
about a priest and yeah, about a priest and a rabbi and
about how a disputation with that works? So the priest goes like
this, and the rabbi goes like that, and then the priest takes
out an apple and then the rabbi takes out a sandwich and
then whatever. So somehow it was like, you know, so then you
ask each one what was happening. I forget the whole joke. The
priest says, well, I said God is three and he said no,
there's only one God. And then I said there's original sin, he
took out the apple, and he says no, but man has to,
you know, by the sweat of your brow you raise bread. And
then ultimately, you know, whatever, he took out the sandwich. And somehow
I don't know, that was the end of the thing. Now they
ask the rabbi what happened and he said, well, the priest said
you have three days to get out of town and I said
not one of us is leaving. And
then somehow it ends and then he took out his lunch and
I took out mine.
So somehow that's what's going on here too. All right, but
anyway, this גמרא Gemara is the most curious גמרא, Gemara, you know,
completely clearly there seems to be something else going on, but okay,
I'm looking for the person that's going to really explain it in
a satisfying way.
Has anyone commented on it?
No, look at the tiny little תוספות. Tosafot. Yeah, right, they give
up. Okay, anyway, all right, let's move on. So he won somehow.
Okay, so they brought him onto the boat.
They brought he brought them onto the boat. Okay,
אסינהו כל
חד וחד. Asinhu kol khad v'khad.
כי חזי שיתין בדרקי, Ki khazi shitin bidarkei, each one went into
their own chamber, but they saw that there were, you know, remember
he put sixty seats into sixty chambers, so each chamber had sixty
seats. So אמר כולהו חבראי להכי Amar kulu khavrai l'hakhei Everybody's going
to come into this chamber because you see the chamber with fifty-nine
other seats you figure everyone else is coming presumably that made them
not resist going like they didn't feel it was a trap because
they figured we'll all be together so what is he going to
do to us? But ultimately he put each one in a separate
chamber and presumably locked the chamber and kept them there so he
actually managed to trap them. So אמר ליה לספונא amar leih l'sfuna
שרי ספינתך shari sfinat'cha so he said
to the boat to the whatever who's he called the sailor you
know raise anchor and בהדי דאזיל bahadei d'azil
while he was leaving שקל עפרא מעפרא shakal afra me'afra he took
some dirt from that place from Athens that'll be relevant to the
end of this story.
כי מטא לבי בלי ki mata l'vei beli when he came to
Be Beli, Be Blili was apparently a place where there was these
like
primeval waters
that all the waters it's basically in the Midrash on Kohelet, כל
הנחלים הולכים אל הים והים איננו מלא kol hanchalim holchim el hayam
vehayam einenu malei all the rivers go to the river and the
ocean and the ocean is not full speaks about these waters of
Be Beli, swallowing waters where all the waters go into it and
they sort of get swallowed up there and just magically disappear or
get fed into some other area of the sea. Exactly.
Sort of like what? Scylla and Charybdis.
No, no this is more like a water black hole.
This is not the Scylla and Charybdis.
Oh that's what that is? Oh okay. Greek mythology. Oh okay alright
very nice I didn't realize that I mean I know between a
rock and a hard place but
that's where that's from. So it's like a black hole of water.
So anyway so מלא כוזא דמיא mallei kuza d'maya he filled some
vessel of water from these from these waters apparently they're going to
work not even in their original location. מבי בלי mibei beli from
this place. כד אתו ואוקמינו קמי קיסר kad atu ve'okminu kammai keisar
when they came and he stood them in front of the Caesar
he said look I beat these guys remember that was the original
story about the seven-year-old about the snakes pregnant for seven years. חזנהו
דהוו מענו chazinhu dehavu ma'anu he saw that they were afflicted like
that they were you know looking pretty poorly these Athenian sages you
know they were not feeling so great. So אמר ליה amar leih
so he said to them הני לאו אינהו hanei lav inhu these
are not the same guys you know they don't look quite their
prestigious status. So שקל מעפרא shakal me'afra he took some of the
dirt from Athens ושדי
עלוייהו v'shadi ilavayhu he threw it on them and then presumably they
like perked up they smelled their original place and it sort of
resuscitated them a little bit. Okay so then אקשו לאפי מלכא akshu
lapei malka they spoke harshly to the king for having instigated this
rabbi to trap them presumably. אמר ליה amar leih so the king
was not so happy with that and he anyway had promised this
rabbi you know that you can do what you want I think
he said or I don't remember in the original story he just
said get me them see if you can get them to me.
Yeah he just said bring them to me.
Okay but now he says to him to Rabbi Yehoshua ben Chananya
he says where was he? אמר ליה כל דבעית עביד בהו amar
leih kol deba'it avid behu you can do whatever you want to
them they're yours they're in your hands. So אייתינהו מיא דאייתי מבי
בלי aytinhu maya d'ayti mibei beli he took this water from Be
Beli שדינהו בתיגדא shadi'inhu betigda he put it in some type of
a vessel okay. אמר להו amar lehu and he said to them
מלו ואזלו לכו malo ve'azlu l'chu fill up this vessel and then
you can go. Okay and this vessel had this magic water in
it. So מלו ושדו בה קמי קמי ובלע להו malo v'shadu beh
kammai kammai uvala lehu so they filled up water and they put
it in
there every bit that they filled up it got absorbed they weren't
able to fill up the vessel. עד דשמט כתפייהו ad deshamat katfayhu
until their sort of their shoulders you know sort of dislocated ובלעו
להו ואזלו ubal'u lehu ve'azlu and they themselves wore away and went
you know maybe like died or something or just wore away from
the effort. And that is the end of the story. That was
very so all of that came from a digression about snakes which
came from a whole discussion about I don't even know about the
Baraita about different types of animals and kosher fish found in non-kosher
fish. Again exactly what the what's going on here is not clear
there seems to be some subtext either about about you know Greek
wisdom versus Torah wisdom or the fate of this worldly orientation and
the worldly success of the Romans versus the not necessarily this worldly
success of the Jews which seems to have been another possible theme
that's going on here. But again ultimately what this answer is is
not clear maybe there's I get a little bit of a sense
in this sort of end story you know that it's maybe talking
about the sense that even though again I really don't can't give
you a clear sense of correlation to the exact description but somehow
the sense that you know all of the success of this world
ultimately you know you know like you know ultimately you try to
fill up this infinite hole but you know in order to fill
that up you need sort of some connection to the infinite and
therefore all of your efforts ultimately are never going to fully fill
up fill up either the knowledge or the spiritual yearning or whatever
something of this world. So it's something about the futility of a
non-religious approach or an only this worldly approach as I think what's
going on at the end.
Yes yesterday we were mentioning that
you know the Jewish I guess approach to knowledge is to learn
it out from a פסוק pasuk right? Like you
had our approach to anatomy with אהלין ohalin you know? But right.
See but I understand like in cases let's say. There's a גזרה
שווה gezeirah shavah of some sort or a לימוד, limud, right? But
like there's no like vested interest in saying that a חיה's chayah
gestation is three years when it's not. You know what I mean?
Or like dolphins, but you know, even if they actually go through
it.
Yeah, yeah, yeah,
it's a good point. You know, nowadays, we in terms of our
scientific knowledge are the heirs of Greek learning, and are the heirs
of about rational, empirical study, and you know, not just from authoritative
texts, but actually, you know, sort of assessing the facts on our
own, and we actually think that that's a major part of our
success as a human race, and you know, and that's raised, does
raise interesting questions about the degree to which the גמרא's Gemara sort
of like scientific knowledge, you know, I mean the רמב"ם Rambam said
a long time ago, don't give חז"ל Chazal a hard time if
their science wasn't our science, you know, they were men of תורה
Torah and men of religion and not men of science, and therefore,
you know, and the whole idea that we can, you know, do
what we can and do incorporate scientific progress and knowledge within, you
know, within our religion. But you're right, the story, it's not starting
about asking like questions about the soul of a קיק, kik, which
might be religious questions, it's asking about scientific questions, and in the
end with that we sort of do tend to side more with
the Greek wisdom approach. So yeah, that is definitely, that's definitely a
lingering question.
No, but what I'm trying to get is like, you know, why
were they, unless they had a text, like in other words, why
would they have thought it was three years? Meaning like, I'd go
look at it,
it's 12 months, or just, you know, like, I don't know. I
really don't know. Yeah, yeah. Sometimes it's still elephants. What?
Sometimes it's still elephants.
Oh
well, maybe they had elephants. Anyway, yeah.
Sometimes the הלכה halacha is affected, like by saying an animal drinks
water and the water comes out and it's not changed and therefore
it's כשר. kosher. It's not, it is so. I know from having
dogs. Dogs, dogs have very distinctive, each dog has a distinctive urine.
When if you've
spoken to, they can identify.
Yeah. But
the גמרא Gemara actually did say that. It changed. Right, but remember
the גמרא Gemara distinguished between different animals' urines. It didn't make a
generic statement.
I think there's no animal, a mule or whatever,
where water goes in
and water comes out.
Look, that is a larger question about how changing scientific knowledge affects
הלכה, halacha, and we raised that when we did חולין, Chullin, and
there are different camps about that, but definitely, I mean, I'll just
say that רב משה פיינשטיין Rav Moshe Feinstein says in principle, outside
of the world of טרפות, treifot, which has הלכה למשה מסיני halacha
l'Moshe m'Sinai aspects, we're open to revising הלכה halacha based on new
scientific knowledge. Now, did רב משה Rav Moshe really do that consistently,
or he only did that when there was a, you know, profound
human need? It really was the latter, but nevertheless, there is that
larger, I don't want to get into that. There is a, but
that is definitely an issue, and there are two camps about that.
There are definitely פוסקים poskim who are willing to reassess הלכה halacha
when the scientific knowledge points otherwise. But yeah, I think I have
the best. All right, let's move on. Next משנה. mishnah. חמורה שלא
בכרה וילדה שני זכרים. Chamora shelo bikra v'yalda sheni zacharim. So now
we have a donkey that has not had, has never had a
child yet, so its first child is going to be a בכור
bechor if it's male, and it gave birth to two males. You
just don't know which came first. So who really cares? Because here
it would be more interesting when it's a question of a קרבן,
korban, because then you can't give them both as a קרבן. korban.
But here, thank you, but here the מצוה mitzvah is that you
redeem it with a שה. seh. You don't have to worry about
which one, you just have to redeem it. So you don't have
to know which one is the בכור bechor in order to redeem
it. So נותן אחד לכהן, noten echad l'kohen, you give one sheep
to the כהן, kohen, and who cares which was the, which was
the donkey that it was for. זכר ונקבה, Zachar u'nekeivah, now let's
say it gave birth to a male and female, and you didn't
see it give birth. You woke up the next morning, and you
don't know which came first. If it was the female, there's no
בכור. bechor. If it was the male, there is a בכור. bechor.
So what do you do? מפריש שה אחד לעצמו, mafrish seh echad
l'atzmo, you separate, set aside one lamb in order to, sheep in
order to redeem it, but it's לעצמו. l'atzmo. You don't have to
give it to a כהן. kohen. Because once you redeem it with
a שה, seh, it's sort of like we learned about מתנות כהונה,
matnot kehuna, the שה seh has no קדושה. kedusha. It's the כהן's
kohen money, property, you know, but it has absolutely no קדושה, kedusha,
no limit about how you can use it. So then it becomes
a civil dispute. So I did the act of redeeming. Okay, now
you, you want the שה. seh. I say, you know what, maybe
I didn't have to redeem it. Maybe the, maybe the female came
first. I only redeemed it to play that safe, but in case
the, but if the, but if the female came first, I don't
owe you anything. So it's a question whether I owe you money
or not. המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה, Hamotzi mechavero alav hara'ayah, you have
the burden of proof. So that's basically the theme. If you have
a doubt, you redeem it in order to do the act of
redemption, but the כהן kohen can't prove that you had to redeem
it, so therefore you get to keep a שה. seh. Okay, so
שתי חמורות שלא בכרו, shteichamorot shelo bikru, you have two donkeys, neither
of which have given birth yet, וילדו שני זכרים, v'yaldu sheni zacharim,
and you wake up in the morning and there are two males.
נותן שני טלאים לכהן, noten sheni t'la'im l'kohen, just that's like a
no-brainer, so you give two sheep to the כהן. kohen. זכר ונקבה,
Zachar u'nekeivah, let's say you woke up in the morning and there's
a male and a female. You don't know which is which, but
who really cares which is which? Because one is a בכור, bechor,
the male is a בכור bechor and the female isn't. או שני
זכרים ונקבה, o sheni zacharim u'nekeivah, two males and a female. And
two males and a female, it's possible you have two בכורות bechorot
here, it's possible you only have one, right? Because what was the
birth order? If it was male, male in one animal and female
in the other, it's one בכור. bechor. Or anyway, בקיצור, bekitzur, the
only way it's two בכורות bechorot if it was one animal was
male and the other was male-female. Any of the other combinations, it's
only one בכור. bechor. Right? So therefore you don't know if you're
חייב chayav one or two. So what do you do in that
case? So in that case, וניתנינהו
לשתי, unitninhu lishtei, alright, וניתנינהו לשני כהנים. unitninhu lishnei kohanim. זכר ונקבה
שני זכרים ונקבה נותן טלה אחד לכהן. zachar unekeivah shnei zacharim unekeivah
noten taleh echad lakohen. In the what's not said here but רש״י
Rashi says is implicit is one sheep you give to the Kohen
because there's definitely one בכור. bechor. And the second case where there
might be a second and you don't know, you separate out a
sheep but you keep it like we said before. Okay now, שתי
נקבות וזכר, shtei nekeivot vezachar, let's say you came in the morning
there were two females and a male. There there might be no
firstborns if the females were first for both of the donkeys. או
שני זכרים ושתי נקבות, o shnei zacharim uveshtei nekeivot, two males and
two females, either way either so there might be no בכור bechor
because the females might have been both of them might have been
first. You have either two, one, or zero בכורות bechoros here, right?
If you have two females, two males, you have anywhere between two
and zero בכורות. bechoros. So what do you do? אין לכהן כלום.
ein lakohen klum. The Kohen gets nothing because you might have zero
בכורות, bechoros, but because you might have two, again what's not said
here but implicit is you do the act of redemption but you
keep it, but the Kohen gets nothing because you might have zero.
All right, now. Is this from the first case? Yeah, what can
I tell you? Yes. Okay. אחת בכרה ואחת שלא בכרה, achat bichrah
ve’achat shelo bichrah, one donkey, we want to make it easy for
you for once. One donkey had given birth and the other had
not prior. וילדו שני זכרים, veyaledu shnei zacharim, and there are two
males. So okay, obviously it doesn't matter which is which, one of
them is a בכור bechor and the other is not. נותן טלה
אחד לכהן. noten taleh echad lakohen. You give one sheep to a
Kohen. זכר ונקבה, zachar unekeivah, male and a female, and you don't
know which is which. So here again you could have one or
you could have zero, right, depending on whether the donkey that had
yet to give birth gave birth to the male or the female.
In that case, מפריש טלה אחד לעצמו, mafrish taleh echad le’atzmo, you
separate one sheep out to do the act of הפרשה, hafrashah, but
you don't have to give it to a Kohen because you might
not be obligated. Now, שנאמר, shenemar, all of this, now this שנאמר
shenemar is not going about all these cases about doubt and עצמו.
atzmo. This is just going on the basic mitzvah of redeeming and
how do you know you redeem with a sheep? Because it says,
ופטר חמור תפדה בשה, ufeter chamor tifdeh veseh, the firstborn you should
redeem with a sheep, מן
הכבשים ומן העזים, min hakevasim umin ha’izim, whether from the goats or
from the sheep.
זכר ונקבה, zachar unekeivah, the sheep could be male or female, גדול
וקטן, gadol vekatan, could be big or small even if it's not
worth the cost of a donkey, תמים
ובעל מום, tamim uba’al mum, it can have a blemish because it's
not a קרבן, korban, ופודה
בו פעמים הרבה, upodeh bo pe’amim harbeh, and you can redeem with
it multiple times. Now what does it mean you can redeem with
it multiple times? It does not mean that if it has to
go to a Kohen I redeem with it multiple. If I have
two donkeys, remember if I said two donkeys I would have to
give two of them to a Kohen, two sheep. So I can't
say oh donkey one on this, donkey two on that, that's a
little bit cheating out the Kohen. No, but what I could do
is, this is the way רש״י Rashi says it, I redeem with
this sheep, I give it to a Kohen, then I buy it
back from the Kohen and then I redeem the other donkey with
it. So even though it's not like ערבות, aravos, you know on
הושענא רבה, Hoshana Rabba, one sheep once you used them you can't
use them again. But anyway you would have to buy it back.
That's what רש״י Rashi says. תוספות Tosafos has a better read which
fits the Mishnah. Because תוספות Tosafos says that in a case of
doubt, if you might remember before the Gemara learned this idea that
it could be multiple times from the idea about what they did
with the redeeming of the animals in the story with the לויים
Levi’im in the מדבר. Midbar. And תוספות Tosafos says what we learn
from there actually is not that you can do multiple definite obligations
on one sheep, but you can do multiple doubtful obligations. Since the
Kohen is not going to get it anyway, in this case for
example where I had anywhere between zero and two בכורות. bechoros. So
I'm whatever I'm going to do I'm going to keep, the Kohen
isn't going to get it. So since I'm not cheating out the
Kohen by using the same animal multiple times, cause he's not going
to get it anyway, I don't have to do two sheep and
keep the two sheep to myself. I can just do one sheep
and redeem two animals on it and keep it to myself. So
as long as I'm keeping it to myself and the Kohen isn't
losing, I can do a many-to-one redemption. That's the way תוספות Tosafos
reads which fits the bigger חידוש chiddush and it fits better in
the context of what's going on in the Mishnah. The Mishnah never
gives a scenario where it says redeem two sheep and keep both
of them to yourself. So תוספות Tosafos understands what's going on is
when there's a doubt you can just use one even for multiple
animals. Now, let's finish it.
ונכנס לדיר להתעשר, venichnas ladir lehite’aser, you take this sheep where you
do מעשר בהמה ma’aser behemah on it. We'll talk about that in
the Gemara. ואם מת נהנים בו, ve’im met nehenim bo, if it
dies you can derive benefit from it. This, so this means that
you know this could refer to the donkey, could refer to the
sheep, we'll talk about it in the Gemara. But certainly the sheep
has no sanctity to it, but perhaps even the donkey if the
donkey dies, we're going to discuss in the Gemara whether the donkey
is permissible in benefit or not before. And that's probably the simple
sense of the Mishnah is if you didn't get around to redeeming
it and the donkey died, okay you can still derive benefit from
the donkey. Okay you have a mitzvah to redeem it etc. but
that does not mean and if you're not redeeming you have a
mitzvah to break its neck, but let's say neither happened. It died,
you didn't redeem it, you didn't break its neck, what's its status?
You can still derive benefit from it. Yes.
So it would seem that you actually have to redeem it on
a specific set. Let's say you have a whole herd, you can't,
you know, and you have like these donkeys, and and this would
be a case where you know the Kohen wouldn't get it anyway,
you can't say all right I'll have all my donkeys, all my
ספק safek donkey whatever, redeem on like my... my herd here, because
then you could just redeem them multiple times. So meaning, if you
have many of them, so then it means, you know, you can't
just say, "All right, it's been taken care of by my fifty
sheep here." So you do this again and again and again. It
means it has to be designated on a specific...
Oh, I don't know if it says פעמים הרבה. p'amim harbe. Well,
okay, you asked me two questions. Number one is, does it have
to be on a specific sheep? I assume the answer to that
is yes. But the other question is, does it have to be
separate acts, or can I just say, "All of my doubtful donkeys
I'm redeeming on this one sheep," according to Tosafot, or does it
have to be separate actual acts? I don't know.
I was assuming the former, but I really don't know. I mean,
the Gemara doesn't even discuss it. It's Tosafot's speculation of how to
read the Mishna. So there's really no discussion in the Gemara. All
right, so let's take a look at the Gemara. מאן תנא, man
tanna, who is this Tanna that speaks about... now the issue here
is we speak about if it gave birth to two
males at the same time, you only have... there's only one. So
the Gemara understands that the scenario would even include a scenario where
you were observing it giving birth and it looked like they both
came out at the same time, because it basically is saying that
any case of two males, you only have to... you don't know
which one, but you give one and you do a redemption by
the sheep. So let's take a look. That gets to the question
of is it possible that two were born at the exact same
time, and if so, what would their status be? Would they both
be sanctified or not? So let's take a look. Yeah, not a
she-ass. מאן תנא אמר רבי ירמיה דלא כרבי יוסי הגלילי, man tanna
amar Rabi Yirmeya d'lo k'Rabi Yose HaGlili, not Rabi Yose HaGlili. דאי
רבי יוסי הגלילי, d'i Rabi Yose HaGlili, if it's Rabi Yose HaGlili,
הא אמר אפשר לצמצם. ha amar efshar l'tzamtzem. There's a later Mishna
that talks about sheep giving birth, and let's say it gives birth
to two males at the exact same time, twins. So Rabi Yose
HaGlili says two points. Number one is, it is possible that they
were at the exact same time, that's אפשר לצמצם, efshar l'tzamtzem, meaning
the Rabbis say, "No, no, no, nothing ever happens exactly at the
same time. It might look in your eyes like it's the same,
but there's a microsecond between them, one of them is a little
bit ahead of the other, and therefore one is the בכור, bechor,
you just don't know which one." Rabi Yose says, "No, if it
looks like it's the same time, it's the same time." Okay, maybe
it's a question about, you know, perception
defining halakhic reality, but whatever, אפשר לצמצם. efshar l'tzamtzem. Looks like it's
the same time, same time. Now what's the status? Then he goes
further to say, two firstborns born at the exact same time from
the same mother, they're both קדוש בבכורה. kadosh bivchora. Both of them
are equally קדוש. kadosh. So now we're saying our Mishna isn't Rabi
Yose, because if it was Rabi Yose, it would have had that
scenario and would have said that you'd have to redeem two donkeys,
not just one, because maybe both are sanctified. Okay, so the Gemara,
he says אפשר לצמצם. efshar l'tzamtzem. So אמר אביי, amar Abaye, Abaye
says, אפילו תימא רבי יוסי הגלילי, afillu teima Rabi Yose HaGlili, no,
maybe it's Rabi Yose HaGlili. שאני התם דכתיב, shani hatam d'chtiv, there
by sheep, it's a special verse that says that they're both sanctified.
It says
הזכרים, hazcharim, the males, plural, להשם. l'Hashem. So therefore, if they both
come out at the same time, they're both sanctified. Here, even though
he might say they came out at the same time, he would
not say the halakhic result is that they both are sanctified. Still
only one is. Only there you have a special פסוק pasuk that
says both are.
Okay, so the Gemara says וליגמר מיניה, v'ligmar mineih, so I don't
understand, why not use that as a model and learn it out
here as well? הא מיעט רחמנא הזכרים, ha mi'eit Rachmana hazcharim, what
the "the males", so only by the sheep, only by the ones
that are sanctified as a קרבן korban can they both be sanctified
at the same time. That's one version, and that Rabi Yose HaGlili,
according to the pushback of the Gemara, Rabi Yirmeya says that our
Mishna is not Rabi Yose HaGlili, the Gemara says Rabi Yose HaGlili
might admit in our case. Okay, איכא דאמרי, ika d'amri, there's another
version, לימא דלא כרבי יוסי, leima d'lo k'Rabi Yose, that the Gemara
starts by saying our Mishna is not Rabi Yose, דאי רבי יוסי
הגלילי הא אמר אפשר לצמצם, d'i Rabi Yose HaGlili ha amar efshar
l'tzamtzem, because he would say that they come out at the same
time, they could come out at the same time and therefore they
both would be sanctified. And אמר אביי, amar Abaye, and here it's
Abaye who does the pushback rather than the anonymous Gemara, אפילו תימא
רבי יוסי הגלילי, afillu teima Rabi Yose HaGlili, even Rabi Yose HaGlili
could admit by the donkeys. שאני התם, shani hatam, by the sheep
it's different, דכתיב הזכרים להשם, d'chtiv hazcharim l'Hashem, the males, so therefore
both are sanctified when they come at the same time, not by
the donkeys. Okay, so now you have two questions. In order to
say Rabi Yose HaGlili's position, you need to make an assertion of
fact and an assertion of law. The assertion of fact is that
it's possible to happen at the same time. If it looks like
the same time, it's defined as the same time. That's the assertion
of fact. Then the question is, what's the halakha? So there the
Gemara is saying, he says by the sheep that they're both קדוש.
kadosh. Would he say the same by the donkey as or not?
Would you learn out from the sheep? That's what's being debated. So
now the Gemara says like this:
בשלמא, bishlama, where are we? Okay, לרבי ירמיה, l'Rabi Yirmeya, it's good
according to Rabi Yirmeya, דלא מוקי לה כרבי יוסי הגלילי, d'lo moki
lah k'Rabi Yose HaGlili, he says our Mishna is not Rabi Yose
HaGlili, that Rabi Yose HaGlili's position would apply equally to donkeys as
it does to sheep. היינו דלא קתני ויצאו שניהם כאחד, hainu d'lo
katani v'yatz'u shneihem k'echad, that's why our Mishna did not give the
example of them coming out simultaneously and then having Rabi Yose, because
it didn't want to, because basically we weren't even dealing with Rabi
Yose, we totally didn't acknowledge Rabi Yose HaGlili's position at all, so
why bother even talking about that case? אלא לאביי, ela l'Abaye, but
according to Abaye that Rabi Yose HaGlili himself would admit in this
case, so תני חידוש, tani chiddush, ליתני ויצאו שניהם כאחד, litni v'yatz'u
shneihem k'echad, why not tell me explicitly? I mean, if it's the
Rabbis, the Rabbis don't even think the scenario is possible, so we're
not even talking about same time because we don't even admit that
that's a possible scenario. But according to Abaye that Rabi Yose HaGlili
admits in the case of donkeys, tell me a חידוש, chiddush, say
even if they came out at the exact same time, nevertheless only
one of them is sanctified. fied and even רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi
Yose HaGelili who says it's possible to come out at the same
time would say only one is sanctified. ועוד, Ve'od, and in addition,
תניא, Tanya, we have an explicit ברייתא Braita that רבי יוסי הגלילי
Rabbi Yose HaGelili says this position here as well. חמור שביכרה, Chamor
she-bikra, a donkey that hasn't given birth, וילדה שני זכרים, ve-yaldah shnei
zacharim, two
males, יצאו שני ראשיהן כאחד ממש, yatzu shnei rasheihen ke-echad mamash, they
came out at the exact same time, or at least so it
appeared. רבי יוסי הגלילי אומר, Rabbi Yose HaGelili omer, שניהם לכהן, shneihem
la-kohen, כהן Kohen gets both of them, שנאמר הזכרים לה', shene'emar ha-zacharim
la-Hashem, the males to God. So the same way it's true by
sheep, it's true by donkeys, that's רבי יוסי הגלילי's Rabbi Yose HaGelili
position. Okay. והא כתיב האי בקדושת הגוף וכשה, Ve-ha kichtiv hai bi-kdushat
ha-guf u-che-seh, but isn't that written by sanctity, intrinsic sanctity, by the
sheep and by the קרבן? korban? דכתיב, De-chtiv, אלא משום שנאמר הזכרים
לה', ela mishum shene'emar ha-zacharim la-Hashem, it must be since it says
שנאמר הזכרים לה', shene'emar ha-zacharim la-Hashem, he learns out from that principle
that it's not limited to that. Now the way רש"י Rashi says
it is is because the legal principle is not what you really
need to learn from the verse. What you learn from the verse
is is that if it looks like two are at the same
time, halachically it's defined at the same time. Once we say it's
defined at the same time, then we ourselves naturally would conclude that
they're both sanctified. So as soon as you grant that point that
we will define it as the same time, then of course the
הלכה halacha should be that both are sanctified. If it's true by
sheep, it's true by...
Just happened to mention it by sheep.
Exactly. Okay. תיובתא דאביי תיובתא, Tyuvta de-Abaye tyuvta, that is a contradiction,
a full contradiction of אביי. Abaye. So now we have made it
clear that רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGelili is not mentioned in
our משנה, Mishnah, but he would disagree with her. He would say
that if it looked like they came out at the same time,
then both of them are sanctified and you have to give both,
two sheep to a כהן, Kohen, because it is defined as the
same time. Same for sheep as for donkeys. ורבנן, Ve-rabbanan, the rabbis,
לימא קסברי רבנן מקצת רחם מקדיש? leima kasavri rabbanan miktzat rechem makdish?
Now we have another question. Okay, you got two animals coming out
at the same time. According to the rabbis, they're not literally at
the same time. So they're not treated as like one whole sanctity
of בכור, bechor, only one, the one that's a little bit ahead.
It's ממש mamash like the יעקב עשו Yaakov Esav story, like this
week's פרשה, parsha, right? The other donkey is אוחזת בעקב ochezet be-akev
the first one. So fine, they're not the exact same time. But
when one of them is coming out, the other one is still
there, maybe a little bit, a half of millimeter behind. So his
body of the second one is separating between the body of the
first one and the walls of the רחם, rechem, part of the
walls of the רחם. rechem. Now the גמרא Gemara very much understands,
you know, it's fascinating, like I don't think we on our own
would have ever sort of thought in this way. We'd say, firstborn,
because it was the firstborn, it's sanctified. But the גמרא Gemara translates
this into a process, well that's right, a process of sanctity, and
speaks about the fact that the רחם rechem
imparts sanctity. And the exiting of the רחם, rechem, it's almost as
if the walls of the רחם rechem by touching and, you know,
by exiting the רחם, rechem, that the contact to the רחם rechem
is what imparts sanctity to the firstborn. That's how it sort of
halachically defines it. So now it's got a problem. The problem is
is that there's a חציצה, chatzitza, there's something dividing the first animal
from the walls, some of the walls of the רחם. rechem. How
is it being sanctified? Okay? So let's take a look. So לימא
קסברי רבנן מקצת רחם מקדיש, leima kasavri rabbanan miktzat rechem makdish, maybe
you only need part of the רחם rechem to sanctify, because only
part of the רחם rechem is touching the first animal. The other
part of the רחם rechem is being separated with the other animal.
דאי כולי רחם מקדיש, De-ee kulei rechem makdish, if you need the
entire רחם, rechem, נהי דאי אפשר לצמצם, nehi de-ee efshar letzamtzem, granted
that you can't, that they're not coming out at the exact same
time, חציצה מי איכא, chatzitza mi-ika, it's a division between the first
one and the walls of the רחם. rechem. So אמר רב, amar
Rav, מין במינו אינו חוצץ. min be-mino eino chotzetz. No, they're all
animals, they're all donkeys, at least we don't have a camel coming
out this time, and therefore it's not considered something extraneous and it's
not considered a חציצה. chatzitza. Now again, notice, right, we would have
said, if we would have asked the question, I think without this
idea of רחם מקדיש, rechem makdish, we would have said, is it
really פטר רחם peter rechem if two of them are doing it
at the same time? But then we would have answered, yeah, the
first one that's doing it, that's the פטר רחם. peter rechem. But
we would have focused on the act of coming out. But the
גמרא Gemara makes it very much object-oriented. The רחם, rechem, the touching
of the רחם, rechem, the רחם rechem imparts, is what sanctifies,
and therefore it's got a problem that they're not in direct physical
contact and has to have this answer of מין במינו אינו חוצץ.
min be-mino eino chotzetz. And תוספות Tosafot points, by the way, to
a גמרא Gemara where it talks about let's say the other animal
is not its brother, but its sister, a female that has no
קדושת בכור. kedushat bechor. Or let's say the other animal is not
just part of it is touching and part is separating, but the
entire other animal is wrapped around the firstborn and none of it
is touching. And תוספות Tosafot says, yeah, that might be different based
on another גמרא Gemara in one of those two scenarios, it might
not be sanctified by בכור. bechor. And this really is important and
we will return to this, the, you know, the halachic way it's
defined how it becomes קדוש בבכור kadosh be-bechor is through the contact
with the רחם rechem at the moment of being born. You had
a question?
I was going to ask the case about a human, human twins
born where you have a brother and a sister or twins and
the brother comes out first.
Oh, so would that be a... Right. So would that be a
מין במינו חוצץ? min be-mino chotzetz? Yeah. That's a good question actually.
If they're coming out like a case of ידו אוחזת. yado ochezet.
Do you really have that nowadays that they can sort of be
coming out somewhat intertwined or...
No, they wouldn't come out intertwined, but one would come out first.
But as long as it's coming out by itself, there's no חציצה.
chatzitza. It's not the חציצה chatzitza in the רחם, rechem, it's in
the exiting of the רחם. rechem. That's the whole point, as it's
exiting. But if you're taking it out—I guess it's not made out
totally...
רחם rechem I thought was—Yeah, that's true,
but that's true, but then the גמרא Gemorah wouldn't... that I, yes,
but here first of all רחם rechem sometimes is used for is
used
like not literally that's not the word I'm looking for
euphemistically to talk about sort of you know the vaginal opening as
well and not just the womb. Actually you know could be look
at רש"י Rashi על התורה al haTorah בעד כל רחם לבית אבימלך
b'ad kol rechem l'veis Avimelech doesn't sound like it's talking about wombs
there, it's talking about you know whatever external openings anyway. So that's
one thing number one and which is probably what it means anyway
by animals I believe there's really no vaginal canal almost. There is?
A long one? It's very close to the opening. Sometimes? Really? That's
interesting in animals. I mean but sheep and cows?
Yeah, I actually just looked up donkeys and it's very rare they
do have multiple births.
Okay anyway anyway so first of all that I think is an
important question which I'm going to sort of like bracket now because
is the רחם rechem here means as it's exiting the body and
רחם rechem is not literal or does רחם rechem literally mean the
womb? But the other point is that we are talking about the
exiting of it although you're right it's not explicit here but take
this from me on trust and we'll see this later. It's not
in the womb that it sanctifies, it's at the moment of exiting
the contact with the womb is what...
So if I'm helping it birth and I have my hands there
pulling it out then it's not actually קדוש? kadosh?
Right so that's an interesting question too. So we will we will
get to all this right? Let's take a look at
the גמרא. Gemorah. זכר ונקבה מפריש טלה. Zachar u'nekeivah mafrish taleh. Okay
now we get to if it's male and female you have a
doubt you separate a sheep but you keep it for yourself because
that becomes a monetary issue and המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה. ha'motzi m'chaveiro
alav hara'ayah. So the גמרא Gemorah says like this: וכיון דלעצמו הוא
למה לי לאפרושי? v'keivan d'l'atzmo hu lama li l'afroshei?
Since you get to keep it why bother separating it out? So
it says לאפוקי מאיסורי מיניה l'afokei m'issurei minei to
remove its prohibited status. The donkey is prohibited and this is going
to be a debate but according to one opinion the donkey is
prohibited before you do the redemption you can't derive benefit and can't
use it. So you're going to want to do this ritual of
redeeming it in order to make now the donkey permissible and you
get to keep the sheep so you get both right? You don't
give the sheep because there's a doubt but because you've redeemed it
in case the donkey was forbidden now it's permissible. Now the question
is if you were to ask me why you redeem it I
would have said because the תורה Torah says ופטר חמור תפדה בשה.
u'peter chamor tifdeh v'seh. So I want to do be יוצא yotzei
that מצוה mitzvah even if I'm not going to wind up giving
it to the כהן. kohen. The fact the גמרא Gemorah doesn't say
that and I started looking last night and I haven't had a
chance to find a larger discussion on this but the fact that
the גמרא Gemorah doesn't say that strongly suggests the idea that the
whole point that there is no the מצוה mitzvah as if you
were to sort of in terms of like מצוה mitzvah points you
know if you want to say it that way as a קיום
מצוה kiyum mitzvah is not a it would only be if there's
a point of the כהן kohen getting it. If the כהן kohen
isn't going to get it there's no point of doing the מצוה
mitzvah of תפדה בשה. tifdeh v'seh. So therefore the גמרא Gemorah says
the only reason you would redeem it is for practical benefit to
remove the prohibition from the donkey. But what again is very fascinating
in terms of conceptually the מצוה mitzvah of redemption is the fact
that it assumes that if you're not giving to the כהן kohen
there's no reason to do the redeeming. That that מצוה mitzvah of
תפדה בשה tifdeh v'seh is only ultimately so that the כהן kohen
will get it. It by the way does fit in also with
תוספות's Tosafos's point that if you have multiple doubts you can redeem
them all on one sheep right? You said that a lot of
those that a lot of the of the laws are defined by
whether the כהן kohen is going to get it or not. So
if the כהן kohen is not going to get it anyway you
don't have to use different different sheep. Okay so anyway the גמרא
Gemorah says the only reason therefore to redeem it then in this
case is to remove the prohibited status if if it is a
firstborn. אלמא Alma we see כיון דלא מפקי keivan d'lo mafkei
as long as you haven't removed that status אסור בהנאה assur b'hana'ah
the donkey is forbidden in benefit. Now it never says that in
the תורה. Torah. The תורה Torah says redeem the donkey it never
tells you what the status of the donkey is before redemption. מתניתין
מני Masnisin mani who's our משנה? Mishna? רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda היא.
hi. It's רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. דתניא Detanya now we're going to
see this whole thing was debated in a משנה. Mishna. פטר חמור
אסור
בהנאה Peter chamor assur b'hana'ah the firstborn of a donkey is forbidden
in benefit until you've redeemed it and somehow דברי רבי יהודה divrei
Rabbi Yehuda stuck in here. רבי שמעון מתיר. Rabbi Shimon matir. רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon permits it. No you do there's a מצוה mitzvah
to redeem but the donkey is has no status totally permissible. מאי
טעמא דרבי יהודה? Mai ta'ama d'Rabbi Yehuda? What's the reason of רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that assumes the donkey is forbidden? אמר עולא Amar
Ulla יש לך דבר שצריך פדיה ומותר? yeish l'cha davar she'tzarich pidyah
u'mutar? How would we have anything that needs redemption and is permitted?
The redemption is to remove a status. So the גמרא Gemorah answers
back yes what's the גמרא Gemorah going to say? תודה רבה Toda
raba thank you very much. ולאו v'lav הרי בכור אדם שצריך פדיה
ומותר? harei bechor adam she'tzarich pidyah u'mutar? How about humans? Right you
have a מצוה mitzvah to redeem and there's no status and forbidden
status of on the human before you've redeemed it. אלא Ella okay
here's the point. יש לך דבר שהקפידה עליו תורה בשה
ומותר? yeish l'cha davar she'hikpidah alav Torah b'seh u'mutar? Sort of very
narrow way of proving your argument. Is there anything that the תורה
Torah meaning but the way רש"י Rashi says it is like there's
a particular ritual. By a human you know we're going to say
that it's five סלעים selaim you know five שקל shekel but it
doesn't it doesn't have to be literally five שקל shekel anything of
that value. So here we have a דוקא davka very particular ritual
of a sheep that indicates that there's some sort of status metaphysical
status that is being that is being transferred. Okay that that's being
sort of removed. So ומותר? u'mutar? So the גמרא Gemorah says ומי?
u'mi? Since when did, who told you you had to use only
a sheep? והא veha רב נחמיה בריה דרב יוסף Rav Nechemia bereih
d'Rav Yosef פריק ליה בשוקי. parik lei beshukei. רב נחמיה Rav Nechemia
the son of רב יוסף Rav Yosef redeemed it with like a
grass and some type of cooked herbs. So now this is quite
fascinating. You know, this is an אמורא. Amora. The משניות Mishnayot never
speak about anything other than a sheep. But the גמרא Gemara says
that the, and the תורה, Torah, but the גמרא Gemara says that
the אמוראים Amoraim assumed that the sheep was to make it easy
on you. That you didn't have to do the value if you
wanted to do a sheep, then even if the sheep was of
less value. But if you wanted to use the value of the
donkey, then you then you could do any object. So גמרא Gemara
says it's not, it's not a big ritual with a sheep. We,
if you want to, you can do it with any object. So
as long as it's equal to the value. So the גמרא Gemara
says בשווי. beshovei. Oh, that's when it's equal to the value. בשווי
לא קאמר. beshovei lo ka'amar. I'm not talking about when it's equal
to the value. דאי לאו בשווי. de'i lav beshovei. When it's not
its value. When it's not its value, it would have to be
a ritual with a sheep. So therefore, והכי קאמר. vehachi ka'amar. יש
לך דבר שהקפידה עליו תורה להוציאו לחולין בשה? yesh lecha davar shehikpida
alav Torah lehotzio lechullin beseh? Is there anything that the תורה Torah
of that, that does not have a, you know, that the תורה
Torah would say do a ritual with a sheep? Because there still
is significance to the ritual. Because it's not value, it's something that's
particularly an idea of a sheep. So there's something and that allows
you to do it even when it's not its value. So there's
this, this like this very particular ritual with a sheep. And how
would that be if it was not, you know, removing a prohibited
status? Again, it's not exactly clear why that's so obvious. Okay, so
there's a whole big ritual. Again, if you, you don't have any
analogy to a case where you use a, I mean, if you
had another case where you used a sheep and it was removing
the status, then you could say this should just be like that
case. But again, this is like sui generis, right? It's the only
type of thing that you have a מצוה mitzvah to only do
it with a sheep. So, but תנא's Tanna argument is, yes, but
if you've got this whole ritual, it clearly seems like it's removing
some status. Yes, רבקה? Rivka?
For, for redeeming מצוה mitzvah with the, oh,
that's interesting.
Although that isn't sort of framed as a redemption, yes, but that's
an interesting implicit model maybe that's going on here. That's an interesting
thought. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute, והרי מעשר. ve'harei ma'aser.
You, so again, you, presumably the argument is not sheep per se,
but that it's a very specific object and the specificity of the
object ritualizes it and indicates that somehow a status is being removed.
So it says I'll give you a case where that's not true.
How about מעשר שני ma'aser sheni שהקפידה עליו תורה בכסף צורי? shehikpida
alav Torah bechesef tzuri? That when you redeem מעשר שני, ma'aser sheni,
you have to use money that has
a, a, an image on it. You cannot just use like pieces
of metal. So therefore it has to be a specific type of
object. So, דתנן, detnan, and we taught in a משנה, Mishnah, רבי
יהודה אומר Rabbi Yehuda omer במזיד קידש. bemezid kidesh. That if you
try, a man tried to marry a woman, this is the קידוש
kiddush of קידושין, kiddushin, tried to marry a woman with מעשר שני
ma'aser sheni food and he gave it to her, then she is
married to him. So that shows you that you can derive, now,
not only מעשר שני ma'aser sheni you only are able to eat
in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, but here you are, you're using it to marry
a woman, you're deriving benefit outside of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, and why don't
we say from the fact that it needs redemption proves that it
should be forbidden in benefit? That's what you're trying to argue by
the donkey. Well, מעשר שני ma'aser sheni needs redemption and it needs
to be a very particular ritual and nevertheless it's not forbidden in
benefit as long as you don't destroy it. But here this man
is marrying this woman.
But מעשר שני ma'aser sheni you have to eat in ירושלים. Yerushalayim.
I understand, but outside of ירושלים Yerushalayim it's not forbidden in benefit.
She doesn't have to bring it to ירושלים? Yerushalayim?
Well, maybe she does, but you're getting benefit. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says like, well, let's see how the גמרא Gemara answers. So
the גמרא Gemara says פטר חמור נמי מקדשא. peter chamor nami mikadsha.
Big deal. Even you can use a donkey to also marry a
woman of the firstborn, even if it is forbidden in benefit, even
according to רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. How's that possible? Let's take a
look. כרבי אליעזר. ke'Rabbi Eliezer. דאמר רבי אליעזר, de'amar Rabbi Eliezer, רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says, אשה יודעת שאין מעשר שני מתחלל על ידה.
isha yoda'at she'ein ma'aser sheni mitchalel al yadah.
When a woman accepts מעשר שני ma'aser sheni for כסף קידושין, kesef
kiddushin, she knows that that doesn't mean that it goes out of
being מעשר שני. ma'aser sheni. It still has its status. ועולה ואוכלתו
בירושלים. ve'ola ve'ochalto bi'Yerushalayim.
So what is the benefit she's getting? That she can't eat it
now, but she can bring it to ירושלים, Yerushalayim, so she's getting
something of value. So even if you can derive no benefit now,
she still is deriving, getting something of value. הכא נמי, hacha nami,
if you were to give a woman this firstborn donkey, אשה יודעת
שפטר חמור איסורא אית ביה. isha yoda'at she'peter chamor issura it bei.
According to רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, she knows that it's forbidden in
benefit. According to רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, that's its status. But nevertheless,
we said that you can use a sheep of lesser value. ופרקה
בשה. u'parka beseh. She'll redeem it with a sheep of lesser
value. ומקדשא בהכי ביני ביני. u'mikadsha behachi beini beini. The difference of
the two, right? If the donkey is worth a hundred dollars and
the sheep is worth fifty, and she's given a donkey for a
hundred that she can make her own by redeeming with a sheep
of fifty, she's given something that has a fifty dollar value to
it. So therefore, the fact that you can use it for קידושין
kiddushin does not prove whether it's permissible or forbidden in benefit right
now. For קידושין, kiddushin, the only question is that will the woman
be able to get some real, you know, practical monetary value out
of this? And for both of those, the answer is yes, and
that has nothing to prove about whether it is permissible or forbidden
in benefit right now.
תניא אידך. tanya idach. Before we go to the דף, daf, here's
the...
We assume in הלכה halacha now that it's forbidden to the woman.
Yeah, that's a good point too. That is a good point and
sometimes, yeah, that's a good point. That's fascinating. Okay, so now גמרא
Gemara says back, so... Anyway, so we actually noticed, by the way,
so we really haven't answered our question. Right? We said, so how
does the פדיון Pidyon know that it's forbidden benefit? Well, you have
to redeem it. Ah, there are other things you have to redeem
that aren't forbidden benefit. Okay, but at the end of the day,
the more natural thing to assume is if you have to do
it after redemption is that you're removing some status, although we really
haven't proved the case. If we proved the case, you wouldn't have
Rabbi Shimon's position. Rabbi Shimon מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, so what's Rabbi
Shimon's reason that says that it's not forbidden? So אמר עולא יש
לך דבר שפדיונו מותר והוא אסור amar Ulla yesh lecha davar she-pidyono
mutar ve-hu asur
because he says, look, when you redeem it, there's no status on
the sheep, the sheep is just monetarily the כהן's, Kohen but it
has no status. So how if the donkey had a forbidden status,
how could you redeem it and the thing you're redeeming it with
has no special status? So the fact that the sheep has totally
a non-status when it's when the redemption is done proves that the
donkey had no status.
I think the fact that you have to break its neck shows
that it's forbidden, so you don't have any benefit from it, right?
Okay, but that yes, but that means that you have to make
sure you don't get benefit. We'll talk about that later. So the
גמרא Gemara says ולא והרי שביעית דפדיונה מותר והיא אסורה, ve-lo ve-harei
shevi'it de-pidyona mutar ve-hi asura, how about when you redeem שביעית Shevi'it
food? The גמרא, Gemara, now this is very bizarre because the גמרא's
Gemara assumption here is absolutely wrong and it's going to reject it
in a second. But for a moment, the גמרא Gemara thinks that
if you redeem שביעית Shevi'it food, then the the money, let's say
I use money to buy שביעית Shevi'it produce with, that that money
has no halachic status. Okay? And even though the שביעית, Shevi'it, the
original food, is forbidden. Now, of course, that's totally wrong. First of
all, the money does have שביעית, Shevi'it, does get שביעית Shevi'it status
anyway. And number two is, you're not even redeeming the שביעית Shevi'it
food because the status remains on the שביעית. Shevi'it. So it's totally
wrong in both ways. A, it's not removing the status, and B,
the actual status does adhere to the money. So רש״י Rashi just
says like at this stage we somehow misunderstood, but it's very bizarre.
So the גמרא Gemara says שביעית נמי פדיונה אסור, shevi'it nami pidyona
asur, what do you mean? By שביעית Shevi'it also the money is
forbidden. And it's not even really a פדיון pidyon because the original
food remains forbidden. דאמר מר אחרון אחרון אסור, de-amar mar acharon acharon
asur, the last type of thing that it was exchanged with, if
I swap a שביעית Shevi'it fruit for meat, and meat for fish,
and fish for vegetable, and vegetable for money, whatever it is, the
last object gets קדושת שביעית, kedushat shevi'it, אחרון אחרון, acharon acharon, and
the original food. Okay? But yes, the שביעית Shevi'it status remains on
the on the thing that was swapped. So anyway, so therefore he
has a good position. You never have something that you redeem with
that is does not have a status. If the thing that was
redeemed with doesn't get a status, so the thing that it is
redeeming didn't have a status either. So the גמרא Gemara says, so
that's one way. In that way, Rabbi Yehuda easily wins, right? I
think, because Rabbi Shimon never proved the idea that redemption means the
thing was forbidden. We have the case of humans where it's not
true. And Rabbi Yehuda makes a very strong argument. If the sheep
has no status, how can you say the donkey had a status?
Okay, so that's one way of framing the debate logically where I
think Rabbi Yehuda has the upper hand. Excuse me, Rabbi Shimon. איבעית
אימא, iba'it eima, if you want I'll say, Rabbi Yehuda and Rabbi
Shimon בהאי קרא קמיפלגי, be-hai kra ka mipalgi, they debate the following
verse. דתניא לא תעבוד בבכור שורך, de-tanya lo ta'avod bi-vechor shorecha, you
shall not work the firstborn of your ox, but and implicitly is
אבל
אתה עובד בשלך ובשל אחרים, aval ata oved be-shelcha u-ve-shel acherim, you
can work it if it was jointly owned by you and a
non-Jew. So remember the issue of non-Jewish ownership. Okay, so לא תעבוד
בבכור שורך, lo ta'avod bi-vechor shorecha, don't shear them, אבל אתה גוזז
בשלך ובשל אחרים, aval ata gozez be-shelcha u-ve-shel acherim, דברי רבי יהודה.
divrei Rabbi Yehuda.
So if it is jointly owned between you and a non-Jew, now
if you'll remember, Rabbi Yehuda says that non-Jewish ownership does not does
not exempt you. You remain half חייב. chayav. But even though you're
half חייב chayav or whatever percentage by you are, if the animal
is a sheep or cow, it doesn't have the קדושה kedusha of
a בכור bechor because it can't be brought as a קרבן. korban.
So that's what Rabbi Yehuda is saying. Yes, there still is בכור
bechor aspects going on here because the ownership of a non-Jew doesn't
exempt you, but you're not restricted from shearing, from working, because ultimately
the קדושה kedusha is, you know, how it plays out that we'll
deal with בכור bechor will be one thing, but it does not
have the קדושה kedusha of a קרבן korban because it is not
fully yours. It has the קדושה, kedusha, but not the קדושה kedusha
that would limit you. That's what Rabbi Yehuda says. רבי שמעון אומר,
Rabbi Shimon omer, no, I don't need the פסוק pasuk for that
as we're going to see in the גמרא Gemara he basically says
non-Jewish ownership completely gets you off the hook, so you don't need
a פסוק pasuk to to allow anything because it's totally out of
the category. So what's the פסוק pasuk coming to do? לא תעבוד
בבכור שורך, lo ta'avod bi-vechor shorecha, don't work the first of your
of your oxen, אבל אתה עובד בבכור אדם, aval ata oved bi-vechor
adam, but there's no prohibition about the firstborn of a human. Don't
work your ox firstborn, but there's no status about a human firstborn.
לא תגוז בבכור צאנך, lo tagoz bi-vechor tzonecha, don't shear the first
of your sheep, אבל אתה גוזז בבכור חמור, aval ata gozez bi-vechor
chamor, but you could of your donkeys if you would want to
shear donkeys. But the point is, it's saying when is there a
prohibited status? By sheep and by cows, not by humans and donkeys.
Those, even though they're firstborn, have no status. So that's another nice
point, right? It only emphasizes the status by the sheep and the
cows, not by the humans and the donkeys. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara says like this. בשלמא לרבי שמעון היינו דכתיב תרי קראי,
bishlama le-Rabbi Shimon hainu de-chtiv trei kra'ei, for Rabbi Shimon I need
two פסוקים, psukim, one to tell me humans and one to tell
me donkeys. אלא לרבי יהודה תרי קראי למיעוטי שבשלך ובשל אחרים למה
לי, ela le-Rabbi Yehuda trei kra'ei le-mi'utei she-be-shelcha u-ve-shel acherim lama li,
why does he need two פסוקים psukim to limit when non-Jewish ownership,
that one פסוק pasuk we should obviously be able to learn the
law. The two, and in addition, רבי יהודה בכור אדם נמי נימא
דאסור. Rabbi Yehuda bechor adam nami nayma de assur. Why doesn't רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda say that you know, human firstborns you can't benefit
from their labor or whatever, assuming they grew up, until you redeem
them? אלא יורם דכולי עלמא שורך למיעוטי בכור אדם. Ela Yoram dechulay
alma shorchecha lemiutay bechor adam. Everybody agrees the first half of the
פסוק, pasuk, אך ach means only, אך ach for sport, not human.
Everybody has to agree that your humans, there's no prohibition of benefit,
הוא דאסור. hu de'assur. כי פליגי בצאנך. Ki pligi bitzoncha. The question
is the second half which speaks about the firstborn sheep. רבי יהודה
וטעמיה Rabbi Yehuda v'taimei דאמר שותפות עכו"ם de'amar shutafut akum חייבת בבכורה.
chayaves bibechora. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda holds normally non-Jewish ownership, if a
partial ownership, you still remain, your part is still obligated. So therefore
this sheep that is partly owned by the non-Jew still is a
מצווה mitzvah of בכור. bechor. Since there's still a מצווה mitzvah of
בכור, bechor, you need the פסוק pasuk to tell me but you
don't have the prohibition of using it and doing work because of
the non-Jewish ownership although there still is the מצווה mitzvah בכור. bechor.
So therefore, וצאנך למיעוטי גיזה ועבודה. vitzoncha limiuti giza va'avoda. Since it
still is in the category of בכור, bechor, you need the פסוק
pasuk to tell you although it's בכור, bechor, because of the non-Jewish
ownership you're not prohibited from shearing it and working it. How the
בכור bechor obligation will play out we'll talk about, but it's still
is in the category but a limited way. And that's why you
needed the פסוק. pasuk. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon would say no, סבר, savar, שותפות עכו"ם פטורה מן הבכורה. shutafut
akum pitura min habechora. As long as the non-Jew owns it even
partially, you're totally exempt. So you don't need a verse for that.
ולעניין גיזה ועבודה לא אצטריכא. ule'inyan giza va'avoda lo itztaricha. You don't
need the verse to allow you to shear it. It's totally out
of the category, it's not a בכור bechor at all. כי אצטריכא,
ki itztaricha, so what is the verse doing? Not to limit the
prohibition of a joint ownership. That's not a בכור bechor at all.
So what's it coming to do? לפטר חמור lpeter chamor to tell
you with a firstborn donkey, it's only by sheep that there's a
status, there is not a status by donkeys. Donkeys have no special
status. I mean you have the מצווה, mitzvah, but it's not prohibited
in benefit. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says just to wrap
up the verses. בשלמא לרבי יהודה היינו דכתיב צאנך ושורך ושורך אתי
לצאנך. Bishlama lirabbi yehuda haynu dichtiv tzoncha veshorchecha veshorchecha atay letzoncha. So
for רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda we understand the possessive "your sheep," because
it's coming to exclude or to limit cases of partial ownership. And
once it had to say "your" by sheep it says it by
the cow as well although the base
of the cow verse was to exclude humans. אלא לרבי שמעון שורך
וצאנך למה לי? Ela lirabbi shimon shorchecha vetzoncha lama li? Why did
it have to use the possessive? According to him the emphasis was
"ox, not humans," "sheep, not donkeys." What's the point of the possessive
if it's not dealing with issues of ownership of somebody else? קשיא.
Kashya. Okay, that's difficult. Fine. Now that we're done with the verses
we still basically have the two camps, that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
says the donkey is forbidden in benefit, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says
it is permissible in benefit. But now we end that there is
a point where רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon agrees to רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda and we'll end with this point. אמר רבא Amar Rava said
רבא, Rava, ומודה רבי שמעון לאחר עריפה שהוא אסור. umodeh rabbi shimon
leachar arifa shehu assur. He agrees that once you break the neck,
then it's forbidden. So Micah to answer you, the point is not
that it's forbidden and therefore you break the neck, but if you're
not going to do the מצווה mitzvah of redeeming then we're going
to ensure that you don't get benefit. And therefore we're going to
tell you break the neck and then don't derive benefit. But it
doesn't start with the fact it's forbidden, it is the consequence of
not having done the מצווה. mitzvah. So it's not "redeem it to
remove the forbidden status," "redeem it because there's a מצווה mitzvah of
redeeming." If you're not doing your obligation then you're going to be
fined and then you're going to be told break its neck and
don't get benefit.
But I mean sort of two-fold, I mean meaning you can work
it and do it its entire life and not redeem and then
it dies and you can't use it, big deal.
Meaning I can use it
my entire life.
Okay, fine. בית שמאי Beis Shamai might try to ensure that you
do it right away but it's a good point, who's to ensure
you do the מצווה mitzvah of עריפה arifa right away? That's a
good question. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says מאי טעמא? mai tama?
גמרא Gemara עריפה עריפה מעגלה ערופה, arifa arifa me'egla arufa, you learn
it out from the broken neck of the calf that you do
for the unknown murderer. אמר רמי בר חמא מנלן מילו Amar Rammi
bar Chama minalan milu and where do I know this? דתניא detanya
we learn a ברייתא, Braitah, הערלה וכלאי הכרם ושור הנסקל ועגלה ערופה
וציפורי מצורע ופטר חמור ובשר בחלב, Ha'orla vekhilay hakerem veshor haniskal ve'egla
arufa vetzipori metzora ufeter chamor ubasar bechalav, so all these different types
of things that are forbidden in benefit: ערלה orla which is first
three years, כלאי הכרם khilay hakerem mixture of the vine and other
things, שור הנסקל shor haniskal you stone it, the עגלה ערופה egla
arufa which is the breaking the neck of the calf the murderer,
ציפורי מצורע tzipori metzora we've talked about birds of the purification and
פטר חמור peter chamor and meat and milk, all of those although
they're forbidden in benefit, כולם מטמאין טומאת אוכלין, kulam metamin tumat ochlin,
they all cause טומאה tumah of foods, they're still considered foods because
non-Jews can eat them even though you can't and you're not even
allowed to give it to a non-Jew, but nevertheless they're still food
because physically they can be eaten. ורבי שמעון אומר, Verabbi shimon omer,
no they're not, כולם אין מטמאין טומאת אוכלין, kulan ain metamin tumat
ochlin, they're not. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon holds that if even if
they can physically be eaten, if you as a Jew can't eat
it or feed it to somebody it's not food. ומודה רבי שמעון
בבשר בחלב שמטמא טומאת אוכלין הואיל והיתה לו שעת הכושר, Umodeh rabbi
shimon bevasar bechalav shemetamay tumat ochlin hoil vehayta lo sha'at hachosher, but
he admits that by meat and milk that is called food because
although now it's forbidden in benefit but originally it was edible when
they were separate so it retains its status of food. Now all
of this is to prove that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon admits that
an עגלה ערופה egla arufa is forbidden in benefit because this is
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon talking and the only thing he said was
food was
בשר בחלב. basar bechalav. ואמר רבי יוחנן, Ve'amar rabbi yochanan, מאי טעמא
דרבי שמעון mai tama derabbi shimon דכתיב dichtiv מכל האוכל אשר יאכל
mikol ha'ochel asher yayachel all food that will be eaten, אוכל שאתה
יכול להאכילו לאחרים קרוי אוכל ochel she'atah yachol lehachilo l'acherim karuy ochel
it's halakhically you can eat it or feed it to a non-Jew,
it's food. food. שאי אתה יכול להאכילו לאחרים אינו קרוי אוכל, She'i
Ata Yachol Le'achilo Le'acherim Eino Karui Ochel, if you can’t feed it
to a non-Jew, eat it or feed it, it is not food.
And the point being, we'll end with this, what
halachically you cannot בשר בחלב Basar BeChalav is the one exception because
it once was food, but the upshot of this is he admits
that an עגלה Egla that the פטר חמור Peter Chamor is not
considered food because it's not permissible in benefit. Ah, doesn't he say
פטר חמור Peter Chamor is permissible in benefit? So the answer is
once you break its neck, then he would admit that it's not
forbidden in benefit, that it is forbidden in benefit, and that's what
we're talking
about. Okay. יישר כוח. Yasher Koach. Happy Thanksgiving everybody.
He doesn't mention עקידה Akeida means to tie
it up.
Correct. יישר כוח. Yasher Koach.